Chandler P. Anderson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Chandler P. Anderson Papers 1894-1953 (bulk 1896-1929)
MSS10918
Anderson, Chandler P. (Chandler Parsons), 1866-1936
18,300 items 63 containers plus 1 oversize 25.3 linear feet 3 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, advisor to the Department of State, and international arbitrator. Correspondence, diaries, informal records and notes of negotiations, typewritten and printed documents, and notes for articles and editorials relating mainly to Anderson's work as a specialist in international affairs and international negotiator.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Anderson, Chandler P. (Chandler Parsons), 1866-1936.; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925--Correspondence.; Cartwright, Otis T.--Correspondence.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948--Correspondence.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931--Correspondence.; Knox, Philander C. (Philander Chase), 1853-1921--Correspondence.; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928--Correspondence.; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924; Polk, Frank L. (Frank Lyon), 1871-1943--Correspondence.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937--Correspondence.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Scott, James Brown, 1866-1943--Correspondence.; Warren, Charles Beecher--Correspondence.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.
Organizations
Conference on the Limitation of Armament (1921-1922: Washington, D.C.); Germany. Treaties, etc. United States, 1921 Aug. 25.; League of Nations.; United States. Dept. of State --Officials and employees.; United States. Dept. of State.
Subjects
Boundaries.; Disarmament.; Fishery law and legislation.; International law.; International relations.; Investments, American--Soviet Union.; World War, 1914-1918--Great Britain.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.
Places
Central America--Boundaries.; Germany--Foreign relations--United States.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; Nicaragua--History--1909-1937.; United States--Foreign relations--Germany.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.
Occupations
International arbitrators.; Lawyers.; Public officials.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Chandler P. Anderson, lawyer, advisor to the Department of State, and international arbitrator, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Harriet W. Anderson, in 1938-1952, with additional gifts from Alan D. Gibbons in 1952 and Chandler P. Anderson, Jr., in 1958. Material was also received by transfer from the Department of State in 1961. Correspondence between Anderson and Robert Lansing was transferred to the
Robert Lansing Papers
, also in the Manuscript Division of the Library.
Other Repositories
Material relating to Anderson's activity as an official in the Department of State can also be found is in the records of the Department of State, Record Group 59, Legislative, Judicial, and Diplomatic Records Division, National Archives and Records Administration, Washington, D.C.sermat
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Chandler P. Anderson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on three reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1886, Sept. 5 Born, Lakeville, Conn.
1887 A.B., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1888-1889 Harvard Law School, Cambridge, Mass.
1891 Admitted to New York bar
1896-1897 Secretary for United States, Bering Sea Claims Commission
1897 Formed partnership with Henry B. Anderson in law firm of Anderson and Anderson
1898-1899 Secretary for United States, U.S.-Great Britain Joint High Commission on Canadian Question
1899 Married Harriet S. Ward
1903 Assistant counsel for United States, Alaska Boundary Tribunal
1905-1910 Legal adviser for Department of State, Anglo-American negotiations for Canadian questions
1910 Agent for United States, North Atlantic Coast Fisheries arbitration, Hague, Netherlands
1910-1913 Counselor for Department of State
1913-1923 U.S. arbitrator, American-British Pecuniary Claims Arbitration
1913-1914 Counsel for Costa Rica, Costa Rica-Panama boundary dispute
1914-1915 Legal adviser for Department of State
1917-1918 Counsel for War Industries Board
1919 Counsel for International Red Cross
1918-1921 Counsel for Guatemala, Guatemala-Honduras boundary dispute
1920-1921 Counsel for Nicaragua, Nicaragua-Honduras
1921-1922 Legal adviser for United States, Washington Conference on Limitation of Armament
1921-1922 U.S. arbitrator, American-Norwegian Shipping Claims Arbitration
1923 Counsel for Costa Rica, British-Costa Rican Arbitration
1923-1936 U.S. Commissioner, U.S.-Germany Mixed Claims Commission
1927 Published Inviolability of Private Property Against Confiscation. New York: Appeal Printing Co.
1933 Sole commissioner, Tripartite Claims between United States, Austria, and Hungary
1936, Aug. 2 Died, York Harbor, Maine
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Chandler Parsons Anderson (1866-1936) cover the period 1894-1953, with the bulk of the material from 1896 to 1929. The collection is organized into Diary, General Correspondence, Office File, Subject File, Speeches and Writings, Miscellany, and Oversize series.
Except for some letters that Anderson sent to his wife during his stays in Europe, the papers contain little that reveal his family life. The focus is on his career in international law, official activities in the Department of State, relationships with key State Department officials, particularly Robert Lansing and Elihu Root, and thinking on important matters of world affairs.
For the years between 1914 and 1928 and for most of 1934, Anderson kept a detailed typescript diary of his thoughts and activities. The diary includes descriptions of public and official opinion in Great Britain in 1914-1915, character descriptions of associates and individuals, and summaries of conversations with Lansing, Root, Woodrow Wilson, Henry Cabot Lodge (1850-1924), Bernard M. Baruch, and others.
Most of the correspondence is located in the Office File. Among the significant correspondence in the General Correspondence series are copies of Anderson's letters in the letterpress books and the letters he sent to his wife while he was in Europe during 1914-1915 and 1918-1919.
The Office File contains records generated by Anderson as a government official and as a participant in various legal cases. The records contain information on subjects such as Anglo-American relations in North America, boundary problems between Central American countries, relations between the United States and Great Britain during 1914, the treatment of American economic interests by the Soviet Union in the 1920s, the Arms Limitation Conference of 1921-1922, and internal problems in Nicaragua during the 1920s.
The Subject File contains papers that Anderson collected as a result of his interests in various subjects. Some subjects relate to topical material in the Office File. Particularly significant are papers relating to the peace treaty with Germany and the League of Nations. Included are correspondence with senators, a paper showing Anderson's contribution to the treaty, and notes on a meeting with President Wilson.
The Speeches and Writings File contains drafts and printed copies of papers, articles, editorials, and book reviews written by Anderson. Most of the subjects in which he was involved are represented. He wrote an especially large number of articles on aspects of international law. Included in the Miscellany series are a biographical file, printed matter on international law, passports, invitations, autographs, and commissions.
Correspondents include William Jennings Bryan, Otis T. Cartwright, Charles Evans Hughes, David Starr Jordan, Philander C. Knox, Robert Lansing, Frank L. Polk, Elihu Root, James Brown Scott, and Charles Beecher Warren.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Diary, 1914-1934
General Correspondence, 1894-1953
Office File, 1896-1933
Subject File, 1910-1936
Speeches and Writings File, 1907-1936
Miscellany, 1896-1936
Oversize
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78010918
Container List
- Diary, 1914-1934 (Box 1-3)
  Typescript diary and holograph drafts.
  Arranged chronologically.
  Available on three reels of microfilm, shelf no. 15,819.
  - 1914, Dec.-1918, Apr. (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1918, Apr.-1922, Dec. (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - 1923, Jan.-1928, Sept. (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - 1934, Mar.-Nov.
  - Holograph draft, 1916, Jan.-May
- General Correspondence, 1894-1953 (Box 4-6)
  Letters received with enclosures, copies of letters sent, and letterpress books of letters sent
  - Letters received (Box 4)
    - 1894-1935
    - 1953
    - Undated
  - Letters sent
    - 1898-1914
    - 1915-1935 (Box 5)
  - Letterpress books
    - 1908-1909, May
    - 1909, May-1913 (Box 6)
- Office File, 1896-1933 (Box 7-55)
  Correspondence, transcripts of court proceedings, minutes of meetings, court awards and decisions, legal briefs, extracts from legal authorities, reports, appointment calendars, duplicate diary entries, notes, directories, clippings, press releases, bibliographies, printed and near-print material, maps. Arranged chronologically according to the office and position that Anderson held while generating the records.
  Arranged by type of document, with key documents first in a grouping, or by chronological order within the grouping.
  - Secretary for U.S., Bering Sea Claims Commission, 1896-1898 (Box 7)
    - Rules, brief, proclamations, correspondence
    - Transcript of interview with William McKinley, 1898, Nov. 19
  - Secretary for U.S., U.S.-Great Britain Joint High Commission on Canadian Questions, 1897-1900
    - Correspondence
      - 1897-1900
      - Undated
      - With U.S. commissioners
      - Between Charles W. Fairbanks and Baron Farrar Herschell
    - Letter to William McKinley from Charles W. Fairbanks, 1899, Feb. 3
    - Official transcripts of proceedings and committee reports
    - Transcript of early commission proceedings prepared by Anderson
    - Summary report prepared by Anderson
    - Announcement of U.S. participation and appointments of United States commissioners
    - Committee assignments
    - Instructions to British commissioners
    - Confidential report on Baron Farrar Herschell
    - Bibliography and lists of supportive documents (Box 8)
    - Forms and form letters
    - Reference materials and clippings
  - Assistant counsel for United States, Alaska Boundary Tribunal, 1903
    - Correspondence, 1903
    - Authorization by U.S.-Great Britain Joint High Commission
    - List of delegates and rules of procedure
    - Briefs
    - Supportive documents
    - Notes and drafts of briefs
    - Lecture by John. W. Foster on tribunal
    - Clippings
  - Legal Adviser for State Department, Anglo-American negotiation of Canadian questions, 1905-1910 (Box 9)
    - Work schedules and letter of commendation for services from Elihu Root
    - Summary of negotiations, 1905-1910
    - Proposals for negotiations, 1906
    - Clippings
    - Subject file
      - Alien labor question
      - Armament on the Great Lakes
      - Boundary treaty negotiations
        - Correspondence
        - Drafts of treaty
        - Reports
        - Great Lakes and the Lake of the Woods boundary line
        - Northwest boundary line
        - Passamaquoddy Bay and Northeast boundary (Box 10)
        - Reference material
      - Conveyance of Prisoners and Wrecking and Salvage Treaty
      - Fur seal herd in Alaska, answer to H. W. Elliot's claim of its ruin
      - Fur Seal Treaty negotiations, 1899-1906
      - Inland Fisheries Treaty negotiations (Box 11)
        - 1906-1908
        - 1908-1910 (Box 12)
      - International Waterways Treaty of 1910 (Box 13)
        - International Waterways Commission negotiations, 1906-1907
        - Clinton-Gibbons, negotiations, 1907
        - Anderson-Gibbons negotiations, 1908
        - Negotiations relating to Joint Commission of Inquiry proposal
        - Negotiations relating to problem of water level on the Lake of the Woods
        - Condemnation of property at Sault Ste. Marie, Mich.
        - Presidential signing, 1909, Jan. 11
        - Negotiations relating to Senate amendment
          - 1909, Jan.-Mar.
          - 1909, Mar.-Dec. (Box 14)
        - Senator William Alden Smith's opposition to treaty and accusation of Anderson
        - Correspondence subsequent to ratification, 1911-1918
      - Minnesota Canal and Power Co. project
        - Correspondence
          - 1907-1909
          - Undated
        - Report on question of international relations, 1907
        - Reference materials
      - Northeastern Fisheries agreement, negotiations
        - 1906-1908
        - 1908-1909 (Box 15)
      - Passamaquoddy Bay boundary dispute, 1908-1910
      - Reciprocal mining rights proposal
      - Treaty of 1891
      - U.S.-Great Britain Joint High Commission of 1898
        - Unofficial transcript of proceedings submitted to State Department by Anderson, 1905, Nov.
        - Report on questions raised by Commission, 1905, Nov.
  - Agent for United States, North Atlantic Coast fisheries arbitration, 1908-1910 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1908-1910
    - Letters received from Allen Bristol Aylesworth, 1909-1910
    - Letters of appointment to members of U.S. delegation
    - Proceedings and awards (Box 17)
    - Brief
    - Argument on servitude by George Turner
    - Summary reports
    - Draft of address to tribunal
    - List of members of delegations
    - Press releases
    - Notes
    - Reference material
    - Clippings
  - Counselor for State Department, 1910-1913 (Box 18)
    - Summary reports to secretary of state
    - Appointment and work calendar, 1911, Mar.-1913, Apr.
    - Letterpress book, 1911, Jan.-1913, Apr.
    - Subject file
      - Arbitration, general
      - Arbitration Treaty with France (Box 19)
      - Arbitration Treaty with Great Britain
      - British-American relations
      - Camisole case
      - Cipriano case
      - Cuban Ports Improvement Co.
      - Favored national treatment (Reciprocity Act)
      - Fisheries, modification of North Atlantic Coast Fisheries Arbitration Award (Box 20)
      - German potash law
      - International Fur Seal Conference
        - Correspondence, 1911-1913
        - Treaty and protocols (Box 21)
        - Report to secretary of state
        - Notes and reference materials
        - Press releases
        - Clippings
      - Maiorano, Ceseano C.
      - Panama Canal tolls controversy
      - Russia
      - San Juan Naval Reservation
    - Clippings
  - Arbitrator, American-British Pecuniary Claims Arbitration, 1910-1924 (Box 22)
    - Correspondence
      - 1908-1914
      - 1914-1824 (Box 23)
      - Undated
    - Treaty and procedural rules (Box 24)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1920, Nov.-1921, Dec.
    - Documents submitted by claimants
    - Transmittals and receipts of memorials
    - Draft of awards
    - Case file (Box 25)
      - Argonaut and Colonel Jonas H. French
      - Coquitlam
      - Adams, David J.
      - Favourite
      - Gerring, Frederic, Jr.
      - Hemming, H. J. Randolph
      - Home Missionary Society
      - Jessie, Thomas F. Bayard, Pescawha
      - Kate
      - Newchwang
      - Sidra
      - Studer
      - Tattler
      - Wanderer
  - Arbitration, 1910-1924 (Box 26)
    - Biographical file
    - Congressional appropriations
    - Clippings
    - Notes
  - Counsel for Costa Rica, Costa-Rica-Panama boundary dispute, 1913-1921
    - Convention submitting dispute to arbitration
    - Opinion of Edward White
    - Report of Commission of Engineers
      - Vols. 1-2
      - Vol. 3 (Box 27)
    - Synopsis of case for Costa Rica
    - Argument for Costa Rica
    - Brief for Costa Rica
    - Brief of reply for Costa Rica
    - Reply for Costa Rica to Panama's protest of award (Box 28)
    - Panama's argument on jurisdiction of arbiter
    - Statement for Panama
    - Reply for Panama
    - Panama's protest of award
    - Map of boundary lines
    - Clippings
    - Notes
    - “Question of nullity of arbital awards,” by J. B. Moore
    - Statement by Panama legation counsel
    - U.S. notes to Costa Rica and Panama
  - Legal adviser for State Department, 1914-1915 (Box 29)
    - Correspondence
      - 1914-1915
      - With Ambassador Walter Hines Page
      - With American embassies in London, England, and Berlin, Gemany
      - With secretary of state
    - Transcripts of telegrams between State Department and American Embassy in London, England
    - Appointment and work calendar
    - Reports to secretary of state and president
    - Certification by secretary of state
    - Subject file (Box 30)
      - Joint State and Navy Neutrality Board
      - Seizures and neutrality violations
      - Treatment of prisoners of war in Great Britain
      - Frye, William P., case
  - Counsel for American meat packers, claims against Great Britain, 1915-1921 (Box 31)
    - Correspondence, 1915-1921
    - Agreements
    - Maracas case
    - Vouchers and receipts of payment
    - Certificate authorizing full power of substitution
    - Report submitted to State Department
    - Summaries of meetings
    - Reference material
    - Diary, 1916-1919, relating to case (duplicate)
    - Clippings
  - Counsel for Costa Rica, objection to U.S.-Nicaragua Canal Treaty, 1916-1917 (Box 32)
  - Counsel for War Industries Board, 1917-1919
    - Correspondence
      - 1917-1918
      - 1918-1919 (Box 33)
    - Index to board's correspondence, 1918
    - Reports
    - Directory of members
    - Notes and reference material
  - Counsel for Nicaragua, boundary dispute with Honduras, 1918-1921 (Box 34)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1921
    - Nicaraguan arbitration proposal
    - Brief for Nicaragua
    - Appendices to Nicaraguan brief
      - Nos. 1-15
      - Nos. 16-30 (Box 35)
    - Brief for Nicaragua in reply
    - Honduras memorandum to U.S. secretary of state
    - Reply of Honduras
    - Notes and reference material
  - Counsel for Guatemala, boundary dispute with Honduras, 1918-1921 (Box 36)
    - Correspondence
      - 1918-1921
      - Undated
    - Documents submitted in mediation
    - Brief for Honduras
    - Brief for Guatemala (Box 37)
    - Corrections of brief
    - Early treaties
    - Bibliography
    - Reference material
    - Clippings
    - Notes
  - Counsel for Morris and Co. Sernia case, 1916-1923 (Box 38)
    - Correspondence, 1916-1931
    - Notice of appearance, summons, brief, agreement (Box 39)
    - Reports
    - Opinion by Barry, Wainwright, Thacker, Symmers
  - Legal adviser for U.S., Washington Conference on Limitation of Armament, 1921-1922
    - Correspondence, 1921-1922
    - Four Power Treaty and drafts
    - Treaties on submarines and poisonous gas
    - Nine Power Treaty (with drafts)
    - Five Power Treaty (with drafts) (Box 40)
    - Credentials of delegates and list of members
    - Reports of committees
    - Proposal for Commission of Inquiry
    - Proposal for limitation of naval armament
    - Addresses by Charles Evans Hughes and Henry Cabot Lodge
    - Appeal by Korea
    - Press release, 1921, Dec. 10
    - Reference materials, clippings, miscellany
  - Arbitrator, American-Norwegian Shipping Claims (Box 41)
  - Arbitration, 1921-1926
    - Correspondence
      - 1921-1926
      - With president of tribunal
      - With secretary of state (Box 42)
    - Transcript of proceedings (printed)
    - Annotated proofs of proceedings
    - Index markers to verbatim proceedings
    - Transcripts of verbatim proceedings
      - 1922, July 25-28
      - 1922, July 31-Aug. 17 (Box 43)
      - 1922, Aug. 21-Oct. 13 (Box 44)
    - Miscellaneous drafts of verbatim proceedings
    - Award of tribunal
    - Dissenting statement by Anderson (Box 45)
    - Draft award of president of tribunal
    - Memoranda of Anderson
    - Memoranda of Norwegian arbiter (Box 46)
    - Notes of president's first statement
    - Notes on conferences
    - Diary, 1922, July-1923, Jan. (duplicate)
    - Press releases
    - Clippings
    - Paper on tribunal by Anderson's assistant
  - Counsel for Costa Rica, British-Costa RicanArbitration, 1922-1923 (Box 47)
    - Correspondence
      - 1921-1924
      - Undated
    - Agreement, list of exhibits, award
    - Extracts from legal authorities
    - Extracts for legal authorities (Box 48)
    - List of documents
    - Press releases and clippings
    - Notes
    - Reference materials
  - Legal adviser for International Harvester Co., claims against Soviet Union, 1923-1936 (Box 49)
    - Correspondence, 1923-1936
    - Correspondence relating to fee arrangements (Box 50)
    - Diary, relating to case, 1923-1924 (duplicate)
    - Statement of claims
    - Translation of Soviet Civil Code, 1923
    - Press releases from State Department
    - Notes and extracts from legal authorities
    - Printed matter
    - Clippings about Soviet Union
  - Counsel for Nicaragua, claim for U.S. income tax refund, 1919-1923 (Box 51)
    - Correspondence
    - Charter and financial statements
    - Tax returns
  - Counsel for Nicaragua, petition for removal of R. R. Hill from Nicaragua High Commission, 1923
  - Legal and foreign affairs adviser for Nicaragua, 1921-1932 (Box 52)
    - Correspondence
      - 1921-1925
      - 1926-1932 (Box 53)
    - Reports (Box 54)
    - Diary, 1925-1927 (duplicate)
    - Notes
    - Legal documents
    - Press releases
    - Clippings
    - Printed matter
  - American Commissioner, U.S.-Germany Mixed Claims (Box 55)
    - Commission, 1928-1933
    - Correspondence
    - Decisions, nos. 1-58
    - Report of American commissioner
    - Clippings
- Subject File, 1910-1936 (Box 56-57)
  Correspondence, clippings, notes, printed and near-print material, and reports.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Board of U.S. General Appraisers (Box 56)
  - Costa Rica
  - El Salvador
  - Fur Seal Industry of Pribilof Island, Alaska
  - Inland fisheries
  - National Civic Federation
  - Pan American Financial Conference, 1915, 1920
  - Peace Treaty and League of Nations
    - Correspondence, 1918-1920
    - “Memo showing changes made in treaty at my suggestion” (Box 57)
    - Draft of Senate resolutions
    - Notes of meeting at President Woodrow Wilson's residence
    - Notes and reference material
  - Prohibition
  - Prisoners of war
  - World Court of International Justice
- Speeches and Writings File, 1907-1936 (Box 58-60)
  Correspondence, bibliographies, drafts of writings, and printed copies of writings.
  Bibliographies begin the series, and book reviews conclude it. Other material is arranged chronologically by date of publication or by date of composition if unpublished.
  - Bibliography of writings (Box 58)
  - Articles, speeches, and editorials
    - 1907, “Extent and Limitations of Treaty-Making Power under the Constitution
    - 1913
      - “The Final Outcome of the Fisheries Arbitration”
      - “Issues between the United States and Great Britain in Regard to Panama Canal Tolls” speech
    - 1914, “Panama Canal Tolls”
    - 1917, “Freedom of the Seas”
    - 1918-1919, “Guatemala-Honduras Boundary Negotiations”
    - 1919, “International Executives
    - 1920
      - “The World Court Movement”
      - 1920, “U.S. Congressional Peace Resolution”
    - 1921